NARRATOR: Egypt, the world's most abundant source of archaeological treasures.
DR SALIMA: Oh, this is fabulous.
NARRATOR: Beneath this desert landscape
lie the secrets of this ancient civilization.
WARD: Wow, you can see why Pharaoh chose here.
NARRATOR: During a season of excavations, our cameras had access
unprecedented to follow the teams at the forefront of archaeology.
MAN: I drive very fast for the thrill.
WOMAN: It's an entrance, we can see an entrance.
NARRATOR: We reveal buried secrets.
MAN: I've just been informed that they discovered something here.
Oh, look at this.
WARD: (Laughter) A sphinx!
NARRATOR: With discoveries that could rewrite ancient history.
Phew, (laughs)
This time, Egyptologists are searching for the secrets of the afterlife.
Alejandro's team discovers a 4,000-year-old sealed burial chamber.
WOMAN: Oh, that's incredible.
ALEXANDER: Bingo!
NARRATOR: John and Colleen decode an ancient guide to the underworld.
COLEEN: The texts, the scenes and the hieroglyphics make this tomb
in a resurrection machine.
NARRATOR: And Susanne makes an extraordinary discovery.
DR SUZANNE: Someone put their fist in to get into the cavity.
NARRATOR: Ancient Egypt is one of the most sophisticated societies in history.
They built the pyramids, colossal temples, driven by an obsession: they dedicated
their lives to prepare for death.
For centuries, archaeologists have tried to decode
the rituals and techniques that the ancient Egyptians
used to enter the afterlife.
Dr. Colleen and Professor John Darnell head to the Valley of the Kings.
DARNELL: We are interested in studying and understanding the past and bringing it into the present,
bring it back to life.
To date, there is no substitute for fieldwork.
NARRATOR: For 250 years, the Valley has captivated generations of archaeologists.
The 19th century was a very productive time.
They discovered more than 40 graves, each one revealing more clues.
about the afterlife of ancient Egypt.
COLLEEN: The sky is so blue today.
NARRATOR: In 1817, an explorer made an astonishing discovery:
the tomb of King Seti I.
COLLEEN: Good morning. DARNELL: Good morning.
Good morning.
COLLEEN: To understand the afterlife of ancient Egypt,
you must study the hieroglyphics and the scenes.
The tomb of Seti I is perfect for understanding the foundations of beliefs
Egyptians about the afterlife.
NARRATOR: Beneath the Valley of the Kings, Seti's tomb measures 137 meters
deep into the mountain.
It is the deepest grave in the Valley.
Ten chambers and seven ornamental corridors were decorated with elaborate
scenes on each wall.
These paintings combined with this immense tomb played a key role in the survival
of the soul of the pharaoh after death.
COLLEEN: Wow!
It's amazing to see how well preserved these hieroglyphics are.
NARRATOR: The discovery of Seti's tomb was decisive in Egyptology.
At that time experts were learning to decode hieroglyphics,
and this tomb gave them a sea of secrets.
They discovered that the structure of the tomb plays a role in guiding the pharaoh to the underworld.
DARNELL: This descending passage is perhaps one of the elements
most important of the tomb.
We deciphered a text on the walls that shows and describes the inclined passage.
that carries, that propels the deceased to the other world.
COLLEEN: Seti I's tomb is so deep in the rock,
which perfectly imitates the architecture of the underworld.
NARRATOR: Seti I ruled for eleven years, expanding his empire by crushing
to its rivals in the Middle East and Africa.
He died suddenly in his thirties, but despite this,
Seti's preparation for the afterlife was exceptional.
He dedicated his fortune and power to building the most elaborate tomb in the Valley,
and he did it quickly.
COLLEEN: It's very important to note that they dug,
They painted and decorated this entire tomb in 12 years.
NARRATOR: The scribes wrote entire books on the walls,
instructions that would help Seti traverse the underworld.
COLLEEN: Calling this Great God by the Gods of the underworld.
That is what we see represented: the sun,
the Great God of whom the hieroglyph speaks, being transported.
And the hieroglyphics are repeated here.
"De du güa ti iu".
The Gods of the underworld.
NARRATOR: The images on these walls reveal Seti I's route through the afterlife.
The ancient Egyptians believed that immortality was possible if one followed
to the sun god, Ra, who was born in the east every day and died every night
and entered the underworld.
If Seti's soul managed to successfully navigate the treacherous underworld
Together with the Sun God, he too could be reborn every morning in an eternal cycle.
This tomb contained detailed instructions
and the resources necessary for that dangerous journey.
COLLEEN: We have arguably one of the best examples of the transition
to the beyond.
NARRATOR: Hidden in the inscriptions, Colleen finds evidence
that not only the pharaoh can make the journey to the underworld.
COLLEEN: Here, the people of northeast Egypt, the Nubians of the south, and Libya to the west.
Apparently, no matter where you came from, you could enjoy the same
beyond like the Pharaoh of Egypt.
NARRATOR: But to find out how Seti made the transition to the afterlife,
The Darnells need to decode the inscriptions inside
from the mortuary chamber.
225 km south of the Valley of the Kings in Aswan,
A Spanish archaeological team is excavating another ancient necropolis.
Qubbet el-Hawa was a burial ground for elite members of society.
These 4,500-year-old tombs offer key clues about rituals
funerary and how the ancient Egyptians prepared for the afterlife.
This is the team's tenth season working here,
but Egyptologist Martina Bardonová continues
getting used to starting at 5 AM.
DR MARTINA: I go to sleep at 12 or 1 AM, and now I have to change.
It's a kind of work jet lag, it's a work thing.
You're here because you love your job, that's all.
You wake up.
NARRATOR: This season, Martina focuses on a new grave.
DR MARTINA: I work as a miner.
NARRATOR: He hopes this corridor leads to a burial chamber.
DR MARTINA: Now I take the top part.
I want to dig to the bottom.
I am considering what is the best way.
The wall is full of termites.
So I continue digging halfway down the corridor.
NARRATOR: Termites are only found near a food source, such as wood.
These insects are a sign that there might be something behind the stone wall.
Crossing the hill, Martina's mission director, Professor Alejandro Jiménez
Serrano is resting.
PROF ALEJANDRO: Perhaps this is the best time of day.
Tell me, Luisa, what's going on?
WOMAN: It seems Martina found an intact camera in its place.
PROF ALEJANDRO: Bingo! Looks like we have another camera.
untouched where Martina is digging. Uhhh.
Let's go!
NARRATOR: Egyptian tombs have been plundered by robbers for millennia,
Finding an intact tomb would be an exceptional discovery for the team.
PROF ALEJANDRO: How are you? -Yes, I can.
Thanks. Tell me what's up?
DR MARTINA: There are termites.
PROF ALEJANDRO: I must step there. -If you can.
Be careful.
We have a wall made of stones with plaster, and it looks like it's sealing something.
DR MARTINA: I suspected it, but I didn't tell you.
Because I wasn't sure.
NARRATOR: If this is an intact chamber,
It could contain mummies and funerary offerings.
PROF ALEJANDRO: No one in 4,000 years has seen what is behind this wall.
NARRATOR: Alejandro faces a challenge, he can't risk collapsing
the wall of the burial chamber as it could contain precious artifacts
PROF ALEJANDRO: Tell José to bring the computer and the camera.
NARRATOR: But he has a plan!
PROF ALEJANDRO: We used this drill to inspect before
to open any intact chamber because we don't know what's inside.
NARRATOR: Consider that it measures 40 centimeters thick.
PROF ALEJANDRO: It seems simple, but it is not.
Ah, Jose.
This is a small camera with light, I'm going to insert it to check if there is any
information about what is behind the wall.
-He's talking about something. -He's a bit slow.
Hey, wait, look. That's rubble.
There are no materials, there is no pottery.
DR MARTINA: I think it's a hallway.
PROF ALEJANDRO: Yes, I think we haven't reached the burial chamber yet.
Archaeology is often frustrating because you don't find what you expected to find.
But it's all part of the game.
The real prize is finding the burial chamber.
We'll have to clear all this material, and maybe find another wall.
We have to work a little harder.
NARRATOR: Alejandro can't see how far this camera extends,
there could be a lot of debris to clear.
In the Valley of the Kings, the Swiss Egyptologist, Professor Susanne Bickel,
returns from his tenth season of excavation.
Today the team reopened a tomb that was excavated in the 1970s, tomb number 61.
PROF SUSANNE: There is a certain excitement, a certain anticipation.
NARRATOR: Susanne hopes to find the grave's original owner.
Could you tell us how the engineers carried the deceased to the underworld?
PROF SUSANNE: Oh, this one's not very good.
It's too small and unfinished.
It is halfway through being prepared.
Why didn't they finish it?
As long as you don't touch it, it won't move on its own.
But um, oops, he did it.
I think going out would be a positive thing.
The whole package will fall.
How tragic.
NARRATOR: Now the team must try to secure the tomb before continuing.
with the excavations.
Professor Bickel has excavated eleven graves throughout the Valley.
In the laboratory they are documenting and analyzing their discoveries,
including human remains.
PROF SALIMA: Yes, excellent.
Oh, this is fantastic.
NARRATOR: Professor Salima Ikram of the American University in Cairo,
She is an expert in mummification.
He is investigating how the ancient Egyptians prepared
for the afterlife through this technique.
PROF SALIMA: There are certain things that we already know about the mummification of different
periods, but of course it is a learning process.
PROF SALIMA: And look here how it sinks.
I think they wrapped the fingers separately and then placed a larger cloth on top,
and then they wrapped it together.
WOMAN: Yes.
NARRATOR: These body parts are further evidence of how
mummification techniques evolved over time.
PROF SALIMA: Embalmers did not always follow strict rules.
Because sometimes something was fashionable for a while, then it was obsolete, and then it came back.
There are different styles of mummification.
NARRATOR: The ancient Egyptians believed that after death,
the soul needed to return to the body,
but if the body decomposed it would be unrecognizable
and the soul would be lost for all eternity.
Therefore, they mummified the elite of Egypt.
The embalmers ritually bathed the deceased and removed his internal organs.
and they used salt to dry the corpse.
They removed the brain through the nose, but left the heart in place,
since they believed that the soul resided there.
Finally, they wrapped the mummy in linen and coated it in resins to ensure
that they would remain recognizable for all eternity.
PROF SALIMA: This is an excellent example of mummification in which
appreciate that this leg looks like the leg of a living person,
and that's because they made cuts in the skin and stuffed it.
They made a statue of yourself so that after you died and were incorporeal,
Your corpse would be hollow and sunken, and this would give you back your body and make you
a more permanent being like a type of statue.
NARRATOR: After a day of digging, grave 61 is free of debris.
It is now safe for Egyptologist Elina to examine it closely.
ELINA: I think they started and then realized
that it was dangerous to put coffins inside.
So they didn't, they left and looked for another place.
NARRATOR: Graves were supposed to last an eternity in the afterlife.
In some parts of the Valley, fine limestone was the perfect material,
but thick limestone like this is unstable.
The sophisticated ancient engineers who built the tombs
They realized that this site was not suitable.
After finishing the excavation of the grave, the Swiss team packs up and leaves.
to another place in the Valley.
In Aswan, Martina spent two days excavating this corridor,
hoping to find an intact burial chamber.
MAN: Should I dig down? DR MARTINA: No, no, no, no
because it's small. It doesn't fit.
NARRATOR: Beyond the rubble, something catches Martina's attention.
DR MARTINA: Yes, it is a cover.
MAN: A lid?
DR MARTINA: I see a part of the coffin, something like that.
MAN: Coffin?
NARRATOR: What Martina thought was a corridor is actually the burial chamber.
DR MARTINA: It looks fine, but there's debris on the coffin.
I can't touch it, it's too far away.
PROF ALEJANDRO: It is a terracotta coffin and the large stone is not a stone,
It is the lid of the coffin.
It measures about one meter long, 50 centimeters wide,
and the body must be in the fetal position.
DR MARTINA: Or it was a child.
PROF ALEJANDRO: This is the mortuary chamber. DR MARTINA: Yes, yes.
PROF ALEJANDRO: We must proceed differently and with great care.
Congratulations!
It's a great discovery because there is no
documented burial like the one we have here.
DR MARTINA: It must have been eaten by termites!
(laughs)
NARRATOR: The coffin is extremely fragile.
Moving the surrounding rocks could cause a collapse,
but it's the only way to see if there's a body inside.
DR MARTINA: Yes, let's continue.
NARRATOR: North of Qubbet el-Hawa lies the necropolis of Qurna.
Date 1500 BC.
Containing more than 300 graves, it is the resting place for high-ranking officials.
from ancient Egypt.
Egyptologist Laurent Bavay has been excavating this tomb for eight years.
At the end of the 18-meter corridor, he made a great discovery.
A rare document called papyrus, vital to the deceased in the underworld.
DR BEVAY: We found several fragments of this papyrus here.
We found other fragments on the wall of the first room.
The papyrus was next to the body of the deceased in the coffin.
NARRATOR: The tomb is empty, and Laurent is putting the fragments together.
in order to be able to analyze the mysterious text.
DR BEVAY: It's one of the most interesting and exciting discoveries.
A papyrus that is actually a Book of the Dead.
NARRATOR: The Book of the Dead is an ancient travel guide to the underworld.
DR BEVAY: This is the document that is in the coffin next to the mummy ready to be used.
Just like a car GPS, it will guide you all the way to your destination.
NARRATOR: The images in this 3,500-year-old Book of the Dead represent
crucial spells.
They helped the deceased overcome trials and challenges on their journey through the underworld.
While he lived, an ancient Egyptian could buy chapters of the book
to create your personal copy.
DR BEVAY: There were workshops that produced books of the dead,
then they left a column of text,
an empty space in which the person wrote his name.
This example was written for a woman, the title and her name, Renena,
are mentioned here which is exceptional.
He must have played a very important role in this family.
You never know what you're going to discover and this is the adrenaline rush.
from fieldwork.
NARRATOR: For Laurent, the most exciting phase is getting started while his team
prepares for the analysis of the text and publication of its findings.
In Aswan, in the cemetery for the rich and powerful,
Martina prepares to open her newly discovered coffin.
DR MARTINA: I'm going to take this off and we'll see.
We place part of the coffin on the ground, we don't want it to break or anything.
NARRATOR: But first Martina must reach the grave.
A Saharan sandstorm blows from the south, and can last for five days.
DR MARTINA: There's a beautiful storm outside.
We can't work like this.
But it's what we have and we'll do what we can.
NARRATOR: The wind speed increases,
So Martina decides to retire for now.
DR MARTINA: This is going to get worse and we'd have to fight the sand.
Brace yourselves guys, this is going to get very ugly.
NARRATOR: As the sandstorm intensifies,
The 182-meter journey to the corridor is a battle.
DR MARTINA: ¡Also! ¡Oh, no, hay no!
PROF ALEJANDRO: It is a dangerous situation because we must extract the remains
humans and we want to continue.
NARRATOR: In the tomb shelter, the team can carefully remove the lid.
from the terracotta coffin.
DR. MARTINA: It's very heavy. It can't be there.
There is this heavy, be careful.
Careful, careful, careful.
NARRATOR: This is the first time anyone has seen the inside of the coffin in 4,000 years.
DR MARTINA: Be careful, there are skies.
It looks like a horror movie.
If this mummy moves, I'll run like crazy.
What an ugly mummy. It's not a mummy,
that's what it seems to be, but it's not bandaged well.
NARRATOR: The terracotta coffin does not contain a mummy, it is a covered skeleton.
with a black material.
As the storm subsides, the team takes out a single pot,
the only object that was discovered next to the body.
WOMAN: Archaeological mysteries.
Not everything is jewelry in Egypt. DR MARTINA: Basically,
NARRATOR: The team will analyze the pot to identify its contents.
Could reveal crucial information about preparations
from this person to the afterlife.
PROF ALEJANDRO: It's amazing.
NARRATOR: The tattered remains of this body suggest
that was not completely mummified.
Why is there a grave in this necropolis for the rich and powerful?
so modest?
PROF ALEJANDRO: The investigation begins.
I'm excited to have time to search for the answer.
NARRATOR: Just outside the Valley of the Kings, at Dra Abu el-Naga,
American Egyptologist Suzanne Onstine hopes that studying the methods of
mummification reveals how the physical body would play a vital role in the afterlife.
DR SUZANNE: Whenever I enter the tomb I am reminded of the responsibility
that I have for her, so that we may consolidate and preserve
what it contains for future generations.
WOMAN: And that one continues.
NARRATOR: So far, Suzanne has found the remains of more than 200 bodies.
DR SUZANNE: When a man named Paneshy and his wife, Tarenu, built the tomb,
They designed it just for them.
But we discovered that for a thousand years other people used the tomb too.
like his grave.
NARRATOR: Suzanne notices something interesting about the body parts.
They were manipulated with wooden dowels.
DR SUZANNE: They inserted the stick into his spine to help him stand.
in the afterlife.
Arthritis would have been a problem, in the afterlife I wanted to be free of that,
and this is how they solved it.
WOMAN: And this other one with Care.
NARRATOR: But corrective surgery wasn't the only thing they did after death.
DR SUZANNE: It's a fake member.
They are prosthetics for the afterlife.
What they did was mummify a group of sticks to replace the arm.
In the afterlife you want to be whole and healthy, that's the point of mummification,
It is so that your soul recognizes your body and you are free from disease.
This is an excellent example of how far they went with this practice.
Maybe this person had a birth defect and was missing an arm,
but in the afterlife he has one.
NARRATOR: Suzanne's discovery reveals the efforts of the ancient Egyptians
to improve life after death.
DR SUZANNE: I'm sure the embalmer spoke to the family,
and the family said that dad suffered from arthritis, and could they help him in the afterlife.
They took care of their loved ones.
Yes, that one.
MAN: Really? DR SUZANNE: I like it.
MAN: I like it.
So, it goes along with these other pieces.
NARRATOR: Suzanne discovered another funeral ritual that helped the deceased.
The tombs were filled with objects that would come to life in the underworld,
magical servants called Shabti.
DR SUZANNE: When you go to the afterlife you want it to be simple and beautiful,
But if there is any work to be done, the figure Shabti is indicated for that.
It was customary to include 365 figures like this,
and all of them were part of a funerary assembly.
NARRATOR: They often inscribed the name of the deceased on the Shabti.
This made them the eternal servant of the deceased.
DR SUZANNE: They also have tools to work in agriculture.
This one here is ready to work at any time in the afterlife.
NARRATOR: But almost all of the Shabti figures were smashed.
along with the mummies.
This only means one thing: grave robbers.
In Aswan, Martina is investigating the burial site.
from an unknown ancient Egyptian.
The tomb is small and unadorned, which is unusual for graves.
from this site.
DR. MARTINA: Yes, of course. Yes.
He hopes a forensic analysis of the skeleton will reveal more information.
DR MARTINA: They completely dissolve.
MAN: Now we're going to do it? DR MARTINA: Now, the job is to remove the bandages,
record what's there.
PROF MIGUEL: Martina? DR MARTINA: Yes.
PROF MIGUEL: She is an older woman
DR MARTINA: Can you say how old you are?
PROF MIGUEL: I don't know exactly, but I was over 70.
DR MARTINA: Wow. The average life expectancy
was 25, and many women died giving birth.
When someone died over 70 it is
I don't want to say it's a surprise, but it's nice to know and finally find out
to someone who was old is nice.
PROF MIGUEL: I am the first person after 4,000 years to see the face
of this woman, it's incredible.
NARRATOR: This woman lived an exceptionally long life,
But it is a mystery why she was not properly mummified.
They carefully removed the bones, so the analysis of the skeleton will continue.
in the laboratory.
PROF MIGUEL: We know your age, sex and size.
I assume the cause of death was an infectious disease, perhaps.
NARRATOR: The team must find more clues to discover why the burial
This simple lady was found in a cemetery for the rich.
At the base there is a rare opportunity to relax.
And Alejandro calls his family.
PROF ALEJANDRO: Hello. FAMILY: Hello love.
PROF ALEJANDRO: How are you? How are you?
DAUGHTER: Good! I got an eight!
PROF ALEJANDRO: An eight in French? Well done!
DAUGHTER: Dad, look.
NARRATOR: Every year, Alejandro lives four months away from home.
PROF ALEJANDRO: I miss my home obviously, but I have the privilege of working
something that millions of people would like to be in.
I'm not going to complain, but at the same time it's difficult.
I missed the birth of my eldest daughter, and it's something my wife won't forgive me for,
and I can't forgive myself either.
It doesn't matter.
NARRATOR: Just outside the Valley of the Kings, Suzanne and her team are cataloging
a collection of mummies that were smashed by ancient looters.
DR SUZANNE: There were possibly 200 individuals buried in their coffins,
carefully placed by their families, and in the process of looting everything was torn to pieces.
NARRATOR: The ancient Egyptians believed that to enter the afterlife,
The body had to survive intact, but for the thieves, nothing was sacred.
DR SUZANNE: The process of looting is devastating.
They destroy the bodies, tear them apart, unwrap them and leave them lying everywhere.
parts inside the tomb.
NARRATOR: These grave robbers were hunting something very precious.
The ancient Egyptians believed that magical amulets could help the soul
of the deceased to reach the afterlife.
One of them was shaped like a beetle, vital to surviving the tests.
from the underworld.
Here, the god Anubis tested the courage of the deceased,
weighing his heart against a feather.
If the heart was heavier, it was evidence of an impure life and a monster
With the head of a crocodile, he devoured the soul, trapping it for all eternity.
But the scarab amulet could help.
If the priest placed it inside the mummified body,
This would ensure success in the heart test.
DR SUZANNE: In trying to protect the body for resurrection,
They placed all these magical symbols inside.
NARRATOR: But this made the mummies a target for thieves.
DR SUZANNE: They knew exactly what was inside, and they stole it.
NARRATOR: Suzanne has evidence of a particularly gruesome attack.
DR SUZANNE: This individual demonstrates the process of looting in a very personal way,
You can see that it is the torso of a subject with only part of the leg attached,
there is no bandage left.
This hole is where someone put their fist to enter the cavity and remove the amulets.
NARRATOR: This poor soul no longer has protection in the afterlife, but for Suzanne,
The looting gave him a unique opportunity.
DR SUZANNE: Although it is devastating, the amount of information we can
to get from unwrapped bodies is much greater than from wrapped ones because we
provides the opportunity to perform a visual review.
NARRATOR: His great discovery of corrective surgery at the time of his death
and the mummified prosthetic limbs are one of a kind.
It reveals new levels of obsession with living a better afterlife.
In the Valley of the Kings, deep within the tomb of Seti I,
experts in ancient inscriptions,
John and Colleen Darnell are examining the elaborate hieroglyphics.
They want to discover how Pharaoh Seti planned to get to the afterlife.
DARNELL: This is an excellent piece of writing, right here.
NARRATOR: Each text plays a specific role in the journey.
DARNELL: "I'm not sure if I'm going to go out and see if I can get out of here."
COLLEEN: Yeah, great. DARNELL: Yeah.
"Those at this door scream when they hear the door close."
NARRATOR: They discovered one of the most important texts for traveling in the underworld,
called the Book of Gates.
DARNELL: This is one of the doors in the Book of Doors,
and shows in part how Egyptian religious texts worked.
It was certainly crucial to navigating the underworld.
NARRATOR: Images from the afterlife texts reveal how treacherous things could have been.
been Seti's journey through the underworld.
The journey is divided into twelve gates that represent the twelve hours of the night.
Each one represents a challenge that must be overcome.
The soul of the Pharaoh uses spells and passwords inscribed on the walls
to continue their journey.
Without proper guidance, Seti's soul could fall into a sea of fire.
to endure eternal punishment.
COLLEEN: These texts are talking about ensuring the eternal existence of the king.
NARRATOR: Now it became the most sacred chamber of the tomb,
where the body of the pharaoh finally rests.
DARNELL: We are in the sarcophagus room in the tomb of Seti I.
We are at the final architectural element of the tomb.
This, for the ancient Egyptians, is the equivalent of a kind of ship for
the soul that takes you out of the earthly realm and beyond to the other reality.
NARRATOR: Pharaoh Seti I built his tomb deep underground.
so that his soul could travel through the underworld.
Religious texts carved on the walls of the tomb assure
that the king has the passwords necessary to travel through the afterlife.
Inside the burial chamber is a huge stone sarcophagus.
In it they inscribed the Book of Gates and it contains the mummy of Seti and his amulets.
This provided him with the necessary guidance to pass through the doors and reach
immortality.
DARNELL: For the Egyptians you had to know all this information,
but then you had to use it, you had to say the spells, you didn't just read the book,
you acted it out.
And not only do you have the amulet, you use it in the right way so that the king
reach the afterlife.
COLLEEN: The texts, the scenes and the hieroglyphics make this tomb
in a resurrection machine.
DARNELL: The ancient Egyptians would love for people today to
He is so interested in what they did and what they thought.
They truly believed that the memory of the dead,
Thinking about the dead would improve the soul's future existence.
NARRATOR: As pharaoh, no expense was spared to grant him safe passage.
to Seti in the afterlife.
But even ordinary Egyptians made sure they were prepared.
In Aswan, Martina and the team finished analyzing the contents of the pot.
which they discovered next to the old woman.
DR MARTINA: We found bits of stone and fragmented insects, that's all.
NARRATOR: Insect remains indicate that it may have contained food.
as an offering for the deceased.
DR MARTINA: The offerings were placed near the head.
They can give the deceased the necessary liquids for the afterlife.
NARRATOR: The remains of bones and cloth show that this person
was partially mummified.
Alejandro has a theory about why such a modest grave exists
in a cemetery for the rich.
Prof. Alejandro: The royal tombs in the Valley of the Kings
They were abundantly decorated with many goods.
But the absence of it on this site seems to indicate that this person was not of class
high in that society.
He could have been a person who worked for important people,
and perhaps his position was to continue assisting them after death.
NARRATOR: The old woman could have been a servant or nanny for a powerful family.
PROF ALEJANDRO: We work to understand the past.
The discovery of the intact chamber will always be memorable.
But we must study all the material we have,
and it's exciting, at least for me.
NARRATOR: Poor or rich, the ancient Egyptians did their best
to reach the afterlife.
The relics, rituals and remains they left behind allow archaeologists to
understand this extraordinary society.
The mysteries of the afterlife are clarified to this day.
Subtitles created by SubTitlePro LLC